Thiago de Paula Oliveira | CV

▶ Statistical computing:
R, Shiny, Maple, SageMath

▶ Computational programs: Latex, Markdown, Office, Gimp, Inkscape, Github

Operational systems:
Linux, Windows

▶ Languages: Portuguese (native), English (upper intermediate)

▶ Research web pages: ORCID, Plubons, Personal Webpage



Solution General Information

Work Address: National University of Ireland, Galway, University Road, Galway, Ireland, H91 TK33

▶ Tel: +353 83 3814459

▶ E-mail Address: thiago.paula.oliveira@usp.br

▶ Date of Birth 01 February 1985, Tatuí, Brazil

Nationality: Brazilian

Marital Status: Married

Summary

Thiago is a Senior Biostatistician at Orreco working in partnership with the Insight Centre for Data Analytics and National University of Ireland Galway (NUIGalway). His expertise is in **statistical modelling**, in particular the study of individual level responses over time. Thiago holds a PhD in Statistics from the University of São Paulo, Brazil. He has over **six years experience in all aspects of statistical modelling** and has <u>published several peer-reviewed papers</u>. Before joining Orreco, Thiago was <u>Assistant Professor</u> and postdoctoral researcher at the University of São Paulo. During his undergraduate, he was enjoyed in a project granted by São Paulo Research Foundation, and involving the Biological Sciences and Exact Sciences Departments. This project led to publication of two peer-review papers, and a conference paper which won <u>honorable mention</u> by the University of São Paulo. His <u>research interests</u> comprise longitudinal data, concordance analysis, response prediction, generalized linear mixed-effects model, computing for statistical development (specially in R software), experimental designs, observational study, development of dashboard designs (specially in Shiny), and agriculture.

Education

2014 – 2018 PhD in Statistics (4 years)

University of São Paulo – ESALQ/USP

- ▶ Title: Estimating the longitudinal concordance correlation through fixed effects and variance components of polynomial mixed-effects regression model
- Advisor: Dr. Silvio Sandoval Zocchi and Prof. John Hinde
- Department of Exact Sciences

2016 (3 months) Visiting scholar - internship

NUIGalway

	■ Supervisor: Prof. John Hinde	
	School of Mathematics, Statistics and Applied Mathematics	
	▶ Development of new methodology in Concordance Analysis	
2012 - 2014 (2 years)	MSc in Statistics	University of São Paulo – ESALQ/USP
	▶ Title: Mixed-effects models applied to hue peel color of papaya of an scanner and colorimeter over time	cv. Sunrise Solo measured by

Advisor: Dr. Silvio Sandoval Zocchi

Department of Exact Sciences

2007 - 2012 BSc in Agricultural Engineering (5 years)

University of São Paulo -ESALQ/USP

▶ Title: Calibration of scanner methodology to evaluate 'Golden' papaya peel color.

Advisor: Dr. Silvio Sandoval Zocchi

Department of Exact Sciences

Professional experience

2020 (3 months)	Postdoc in Biostatistics	NUIGalway
	 Supervisor: Prof. Dr. John Newell Aspire Academy research collaboration project School of Mathematics, Statistics & Applied Maths; and Insight Centre for Date 	ita Analytics
2019 (8 months)	Postdoc in Biostatistics	NUIGalway
	 Supervisor: Prof. Dr. John Newell Statistical modeling for optimizing athlete performance School of Mathematics, Statistics & Applied Maths; Orreco; and Insight C Analytics 	entre for Data
2018-2019 (10 months)	Postdoc in Statistics University of	f São Paulo – ESALQ/USP
	 Advisor: Prof. Dr. Clarice Garcia Borges Demétrio Title: Estimation of the longitudinal concordance correlation function: The 1c Department of Exact Sciences 	c package

>>> Volunteer experience

2017 - 2019

Class tutor in Calculus at University of São Paulo – ESALQ/USP (5 months) 2016 2015 Class tutor in Statistics at University of São Paulo - ESALQ/USP (5 months)

Assistant Professor at University of São Paulo - ESALQ/USP (18 months)

Research experience

Generalized linear mixed-effects models (Classical and Bayesian)
Concordance analysis (Agreement, precision, and accuracy measures)
Bootstrap methods for confidence intervals (Non-parametric and parametric)
Experimental Designs (Complete and Incomplete Blocks, Latin Square, Full factorial, Fractional Factorial, Split-Plot, Central Composite, Nested designs)
Longitudinal data and Observational Studies
State space models (ARMA, ARIMA and Random Walk models)
Digital Image Analysis, Vegetal Production, Post-Harvest
Development of R packages, Dashboard Design, and Webpages (Github)

>>> Publications

Submitted manuscript

Submitted manuscript

	l able	1: Publication	ns summary	
	Article	R Package	Abstract	Manuscript
Number	4	1	11	2

Papers Submitted in Peer-Reviewed Journals
Oliveira, T.P.; Moral, R. A.; Hinde, J.; Zocchi, S. S.; Demetrio, C. G. B. Estimation of the longitudinal concordance correlation function in R: The LCC package. PeerJ - Life and Environment Science . Submitted in March 2020.
Kleina, H. T.; Kudlawiec, K.; Esteves, M. B.; Daibó, M.; Oliveira, T.P. ; Maluta, N.; Lopes, J. S.; Mio, L. M. Association of leaf morphology, vector settling and feeding behavior with resistence of plum genotypes to leaf scald disease. European Journal of Plant Pathology . Submitted in April 2020.

Papers in Peer-Reviewed Journals Popin, G. V.; Santos, A. K. B.; Oliveira, T.P.; Camargo, P. B.; Cerri, C. E. P.; Siqueira-Neto; Article M. Sugarcane straw management for bioenergy: effects of global warming on greenhouse gas emissions and soil carbon storage. Mitigation and Adaptation Strategies for Global Change, 2019. Link: https://doi.org/10.1007/s11027-019-09880-7 Esteves, M. B.; Kleina, H. T.; Sales, T. M.; Oliveira, T.P.; Lara, I. A. R.; Almeida, R. P. P.; Article Coletta-Filho, H. D.; Lopes, J. R. S. Transmission efficiency of Xylella fastidiosa subsp. pauca sequence types by sharpshooter vectors after in vitro acquisition. The American Phytopathological Society, v. 109, no.2, 2019. Link: https://doi.org/10.1094/PHYTO-07-18-0254-FI Oliveira, T.P.; Hinde, J.; Zocchi, S. S. Longitudinal Concordance Correlation Function Based Article on Variance Components: An Application in Fruit Color Analysis. Journal of Agricultural, Biological, and Environmental Statistics, v. 23, p. 233-254, 2018. Link: https://doi.org/ 10.1007/s13253-018-0321-1 Oliveira, T.P.; Zocchi, S. S.; Jacomino, A. P. Measuring color hue in 'Sunrise Solo' papaya Article using a flatbed scanner. Revista Brasileira de Fruticultura, v. 39, p. e-911, 2017. Link: http://dx.doi.org/10.1590/0100-29452017911

R package

Oliveira, T.P.; Moral, R. A.; Hinde, J.; Zocchi, S. S.; Demetrio, C. G. B. Icc: Longitudinal Concordance Correlation, R package version 1.0.2, 2018. See also https://github.com/Prof-ThiagoOliveira/lcc

Proceedings

Extended abstract

Oliveira, T.P.; Moral, R.A.; Hinde, J.; Zocchi, S.S.; Demétrio, C.G.B. The longitudinal concordance correlation. **In: 34**th **International Workshop on Statistical Modelling**, 2019, Guimarães. Proceedings of the 34th International Workshop on Statistical Modelling, 2019. v. 2.

Abstract

Zocchi, S.S.; **Oliveira, T.P.** Propagação de Penicillium em Iaranja (Citrus cinensis): estimulando o aprendizado de cálculo. 1° Oficina para o desenvolvimento docente de 2017, "Novas abordagens de ensino - compartilhando experiências na ESALQ", 2017

Abstract

Oliveira, T.P.; Hinde, J.; Zocchi, S.S. Longitudinal Concordance correlation function based on variance components: an application in fruit color analysis. NUIG Statistics MiniSymposium, 2016.

Extended abstract

Oliveira, T.P.; Moral, R.A.; Hinde, J.; Demétrio, C.G.B.; Zocchi, S.S.; Zanardo, A.B.R.; Delalibera Jr., I. Generalized linear mixed models applied to overdispersed proportion data in a fungal occurrence study. **In: 30**th **International Workshop on Statistical Modelling**, 2015, Linz. Proceedings of the 30th International Workshop on Statistical Modelling, 2015. v. 2. p. 203-206.

Abstract

Oliveira, T.P.; Moral, R.A.; Hinde, J.; Demétrio, C.G.B.; Zocchi, S.S. Generalized linear mixed models: an application in fungal occurrence data. In: 60° Reunião Anual da Região Brasileira da Sociedade Internacional de Biometria e 16° Simpósio de Estatística Aplicada à Experimentação Agronômica, 2015, Presidente Prudente. Reunião Anual da Região Brasileira da Sociedade Internacional de Biometria, n. 60, Presidente Prudente, 2015. 172 p., 2015.

Abstract

Oliveira, T.P.; Zocchi, S.S.; Ferreira, I. E.P. Mixed models for analysis of hue peel colour of papaya (Carica papaya L.) cv. Sunrise Solo, measured along time by means of a scanner and a colorimeter. In: XXVII International Biometric Conference, 2014, Florence, Italy. Proceedings of XXVII International Biometric Conference, 2014. v. 1.

Abstract

Oliveira, T.P.; Zocchi, S.S. Mixed models for analysis of hue peel color of papaya (Carica papaya L.) cv. 'Sunrise Solo', measured along time by means of a scanner and a colorimeter. I Workshop on Experimental Statistics e IV Encontro dos Alunos do PPG em Agronomia (Estatística e experimentação agrnômica), 2014.

Extended abstract

Oliveira, T.P.; Zocchi, S. S. . Análise de dados circulares com aplicação em tonalidade da cor de casca de mamão 'Sunrise Solo'. In: **58**° **Reunião Anual da Região Brasileira da Sociedade Internacional de Biometria e 15**° **Simpósio de Estatística Aplicada à Esperimentação Agronômica**, 2013, Campina Grande. Anais..., 2013. p. 202.

Extended abstract

Oliveira, T.P.; Zocchi, S. S. Análise de dados circulares com aplicação em tonalidade da cor de casca de mamão 'Sunrise Solo'. In: 58º Reunião Anual da Região Brasileira da Sociedade Internacional de Biometria e 15º Simpósio de Estatística Aplicada à Esperimentação Agronômica, 2013, Campina Grande. Anais..., 2013. p. 202.

Abstract

Oliveira, T.P.; Zocchi, S. S. Modelos lineares de efeitos mistos: um estudo de caso. Encontro dos Alunos do Programa de Pós-Graduação em Estatística e e Experimentação Agronômica, 2013

Abstract

Camara, G. M. S.; Oliveira, T.P.; Navarro, B. L.; Brigliadori, L. D. Crescimento e produtividade de soja em três arranjos espaciais. In: VI Congresso Brasileiro de Soja, 2012, Cuiabá-MT. Anais. Londrina-PR: Embrapa Soja, 2012. v. 1. p. 151-153.

Thesis

Theses

Oliveira, T.P. Estimating the longitudinal concordance correlation through fixed effects and variance components of polynomial mixed-effects regression model. University of São Paulo, 2018

Oliveira, T.P. Mixed-effects models applied to hue peel color of papaya cv. Sunrise Solo measured by an scanner and colorimeter over time. University of São Paulo, 2014

>>> Revie	ewer	
2019	Biocontrol Science and Technology, Taylor & Francis	Link
	▶ Number of papers reviewed: 1	
2020	PeerJ - Life and Environment	Link
	Number of papers reviewed: 2	

Masters and PhD Examiners

Nascimento, C.O.; Lara, I.A.R. Analysis of color peel of the papaya cv. Sunrise Solo through of the mixed linear regression model. Thesis (Master's Degree in Statistics) – University of São Paulo, Piracicaba, Brazil.

Awards

2010 Honorable Mention at the 18^{th} USP International Symposium of Undergraduate Research, University of São Paulo.

Extracurricular courses (last 5 years)

2019	Survival Analysis in R. DataCamp, USA. (4h)
2019	Building Web Applications in R with Shiny: Case Studies Course. DataCamp, USA. (4h)
2019	Building Dashboards with shinydashboard. DataCamp, USA. (4h)
2019	Building Web Applications in R with Shiny. DataCamp, USA. (4h)
2019	Introduction to Python. DataCamp, USA. (4h)
2019	Statistical Modeling in R (Part 1). DataCamp, USA. (4h)
2019	Intermediate R. DataCamp, USA. (6h)
2019	Introduction to R. DataCamp, USA. (4h)
2018	Machine Learning Toolbox. DataCamp, USA. (4h)
2016	Longitudinal and Incomplete Data – USP (30h)
2015	Short curse on Regression Models – Coursera, MOOC, USA (36h)
2015	Short curse on Dimensionality Reduction – USP
2015	Additive Generalized Models with P-splines – RBras
2015	Exploring interactive graphical interfaces in R – RBras

2015	Exploring the	Flexibility of	Linear Mixed	Models – RBras

2015 Special Topics in Multivariate Analysis – RBras

>>> Event participation (last 5 years)

2019	The Inaugural Young-ISA Meeting – Maynooth, Co. Kildare, Ireland
2019	$34^{\it th}$ meeting of the International Workshop on Statistical Modelling (IWSM) – Guimarães, Portugal.
2016	NUIG Statistics MiniSymposium. Longitudinal Concordance correlation function based on variance components: an application in fruit color analysis.
2015	$30^{\it th}$ meeting of the International Workshop on Statistical Modelling (IWSM) – Linz, Vienna.
2015	60 th meeting of the Brazilian Region International Biometric Society (RBras) e 16° "Simpósio de Estatística Aplicada à Experimentação Agronômica" – Presidente Prudente, SP, Brazil
2015	How to Write for and Get Published in Scientific Journals – Piracicaba, SP, Brazil
2014	II Workshop on Longitudinal and Incomplete Data – Piracicaba, SP, Brazil
2014	l Workshop on Experimental Statistics e IV "Encontro dos Alunos do PPG em Agronomia" – Piracicaba, SP, Brazil

Teaching Experience

Taught Modules	
2018	LCE0602 Experimental Statistics, University of São Paulo, Piracicaba, Brazil, <i>Agricultural Engineering programme</i> , August-December.
2018	LCE0220 Calculus II, University of São Paulo, Piracicaba, Brazil, <i>Agricultural Engineering programme</i> , August - December.
2018	LCE0120 Calculus I, University of São Paulo, Piracicaba, Brazil, <i>Agricultural Engineering programme</i> , August - December.
2018	LCE0120 Calculus I, University of São Paulo, Piracicaba, Brazil, Agricultural Engineering programme, February - June.
2018	LCE0220 Calculus II, University of São Paulo, Piracicaba, Brazil, <i>Agricultural Engineering programme</i> , February - June.
2018	LCE0130 Differential and Integral Calculus, University of São Paulo, Piracicaba, Brazil, <i>Food Science programme</i> , February - June.
2017	LCE0602 Experimental Statistics, University of São Paulo, Piracicaba, Brazil, <i>Agricultural Engineering programme</i> , August - December.
2017	LCE0120 Calculus II, University of São Paulo, Piracicaba, Brazil, <i>Agricultural Engineering programme</i> , August - December.
	Taught Short Courses
2018	I Workshop on Introduction to Experimental Design, University of São Paulo, Piracicaba, Brazil

2016	LCE0120 - Calculus I, University of São Paulo, Piracicaba, Brazil, taught by Dr. Silvio Sandoval Zocchi for undergraduate students of the Agricultural Engineering programme, 120h
2015	LLCE0220 Calculus II, University of São Paulo, Piracicaba, Brazil, taught by Prof. Idemauro Antonio Rodrigues de Lara for undergraduate students of the Agricultural Engineering programme, August-December, 120h
2015	LLCE0211 Statistics, University of São Paulo, Piracicaba, Brazil, taught by Dr. Silvio Sandoval Zocchi for undergraduate students of the Agricultural Engineering programme, February-June, 120h
2013	LLCE0220 Calculus II, University of São Paulo, Piracicaba, Brazil, taught by Prof. Idemauro Antonio Rodrigues de Lara for undergraduate students of the Agricultural Engineering programme, August-December, 120h
2013	LLCE0166 Calculus and Mathematics Applied to Food Sciences, University of São Paulo, Piracicaba, Brazil, taught by Dr. Silvio Sandoval Zocchi for undergraduate students of the Food Sciences programme, February-June, 120h

DDD Lectured workshops and invited talks

2020	Estimating NBA athlete performance using hierarchical models, National University of Ireland Galway, Ireland, 21 April 2020
2019	Modelling menstrual cycle length using state space models. The Inaugural Young-ISA Meeting – Maynooth, Ireland
2016	Longitudinal concondance correlation function based on variance components: an application in fruit color – NUI Galway

>>> Professional Websites and Apps

Github	https://github.com/Prof-ThiagoOliveira	Link
ІссАрр	https://prof-thiagooliveira.shinyapps.io/lccApp/	Link
Calculus	https://prof-thiagooliveira.github.io/calculus/	Link

>>> Fellowship

2011

2012-2013 Coordination of Improvement of Higher Education Personnel CAPES		 Scientific initiation / Advisor: Prof. Silvio Sandoval Zocchi Process number: 2010/16955-1 Grants awarded: approximately £3,000 	
	2012-2013		CAPES

- ▶ Master / Advisor: Prof. Silvio Sandoval Zocchi
- ▶ Project: Mixed effects models applied to hue peel color of papaya (Carica papaya L.) cv. "Sunrise Solo" measured over time using an scanner and a colorimeter
- **▶** Grants awarded: approximately £15,082

2014-2017 National Council for Scientific and Technological Development

São Paulo Research Foundation

CNPq

FAPESP

	 PhD / Advisor: Prof. Silvio Sandoval Zocchi Project: Estimating the longitudinal concordance correlation through fixed effects are components of polynomial mixed-effects regression model Grants awarded: approximately £26,543 	nd variance
2018-2019	Coordination of Improvement of Higher Education Personnel	CAPES
	 Postdoctoral Researcher / Coordinator: Prof^a. Clarice G. B. Demétrio Project: Estimation of Longitudinal Concordance Correlation Function: The lcc pa Grants awarded: approximately £7,000 	ckage
2019	Science Foundation Ireland	SFI
	 Postdoctoral Researcher in Biostatistics / Coordinator: Prof. John Newell Project: Development of statistical model with application in athlete performance Project Funding: €12,417,097 	
	Caianaa Farmatatian lualand	SFI
2020	Science Foundation Ireland	

References

Pro	f. John Hinde	NUIGalway
> F	Phone: +353 (0) 91 492043	
> E	mail: john.hinde@nuigalway.ie	
Dr.	Rafael de Andrade Moral	Maynooth University
» F	Phone: +353 (1) 708 6645	
» E	mail: rafael.deandrademoral@mu.ie	
Pro	f. John Newell	NUIGalway
» F	Phone: +353 (0) 91 524411	
> E	Email: john.newell@nuigalway.ie	
Pro	f. Silvio Sandoval Zocchi	ESALQ/USP
> F	Phone:+55 (19) 3429.4127	
> E	Email: sszocchi@usp.br	
Pro	f. Clarice Garcia Borges Demétrio	ESALQ/USP
> F	Phone:+55 (19) 3429.4127	

Address: National University of Ireland Galway, School of Mathematics, Statistics & Applied Mathematics, University Road, Galway, Ireland. H91 TK33

▶ Email: clarice.demetrio@usp.br